<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Be a Better Leader</title>
    <description>Practical notes on leadership improvements</description>
    <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 17:02:08 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 17:02:08 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Test</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a b&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/test.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/test.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quiet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a brief take-aways after reading one more good book - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Quiet-power-introverts-world-talking-ebook/dp/B0074YVW1G/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;colid=35LOWQ4FF0B1T&amp;amp;sr=&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;coliid=I2AOFX45GMPDML&quot;&gt;Quiet by Susan Cain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/quiet-196x300.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;quiet&quot; class=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book helps you to understand people better, to know how different they can be and what their behavior could mean, how to embrace your quietness and make it work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes I liked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We don’t need giant personalities to transform companies. We need leaders who build not their own egos but the institutions they run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Open-plan offices have been found to reduce productivity and impair memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Studies have shown that performance gets worse as group size increases: groups of nine generate fewer and poorer ideas compared to groups of six, which do worse than groups of four.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Another study, of 38,000 knowledge workers across different sectors, found that the simple act of being interrupted is one of the biggest barriers to productivity. Even multitasking, that prized feat of modern-day office warriors, turns out to be a myth. Scientists now know that the brain is incapable of paying attention to two things at the same time. What looks like multitasking is really switching back and forth between multiple tasks, which reduces productivity and increases mistakes by up to 50 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The “Bus to Abilene” anecdote reveals our tendency to follow those who initiate action— any action. We are similarly inclined to empower dynamic speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the managers, who does “people management” (I so don’t like this phrase, but haven’t found a better one), I would definitely recommend reading this book, or at least watch for this 20 minutes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/susan_cain_the_power_of_introverts&quot;&gt;Susan Cain TED talk&lt;/a&gt;. The talk is not that good and detailed as the book, but still it gives you the main idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: By the middle of the book I’ve started thinking that I am more introvert than extrovert, though always thought opposite :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/quiet.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/quiet.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Here is how I spend my weekdays as unemployed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was always curious what do people do all day long if they do not work!? For me it was frightening question. Since I can remember all my weekdays were preoccupied with important activities and rather strict schedule: first, school and after school lectures, then university and different kinds of part time jobs and later, professionally developing software for ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/vintage-housewife-276x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image courtesy of Austin Fashion Week&quot; class=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all the weekdays were predefined for me: wakeup in the morning, travel to work, work, travel home, yoga class, two-three hours of a free personal time, go to sleep. Roughly rounding: 11 hours work related activities and 5 hours of non work related activities and 8 hours for sleep. So what do you do 16 hours a day if you don’t work!!??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 months ago I decided to leave my dream job and move to Seattle in search for even better one. So for 5 months I’m unemployed and have 16 hours of a personal time everyday in my possession. And believe me, from the day one of my unemployment I started getting this frightening “What do you do all day long” question very often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2015/01/06/upshot/how-nonemployed-americans-spend-their-weekdays-men-vs-women.html?_r=0&amp;amp;abt=0002&amp;amp;abg=0&quot;&gt;interesting statistics on how do Americans spend their weekdays&lt;/a&gt; and decided to share my daily routine. Here is how my weekday agenda looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7:00 Wake up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7:30 - 8:30 Brisk walk (I escort my husband to his office and come back home)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8:30 - 12:00 &lt;strong&gt;News &amp;amp; job search&lt;/strong&gt;: catching-up with news and blogs on software development and management (mostly, via Feedly) or perform job search activities, such as: searching for new connections on LinkedIn, writing emails to recruiters, filling in job applications forms, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00 - 13:00 Workout in a gym &amp;amp; short daily yoga class (while working out in a gym I try to listen to various podcasts)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:00 - 13:30 Lunch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:30 - 15:00 &lt;strong&gt;Listening to lectures&lt;/strong&gt; (currently it’s Princeton University Algorithms course provided by Coursera or MIT Open Courseware Computer Science lectures)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/github-300x181.png&quot; alt=&quot;github activity&quot; class=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15:00 - 18:30 &lt;strong&gt;Programming&lt;/strong&gt; (I decided to learn Ruby, so now I’m implementing various classic algorithms, data structures and solve interesting coding challenges using Ruby)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not say, that all days are the same, the energy level is high and I wish to do all these activities instead of procrastinating on the internet or doing something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/lounge-150x150.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lounge&quot; class=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when these days come, I go out to work in some public place: either lounge areas in my building or some coffee shop in a neighborhood. This helps to overcome laziness and to stay focused on a task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/starbucks-150x150.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;starbucks&quot; class=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this agenda, at least twice a month I attend different Agile, Project Management, Software Development Management and similar meet-ups and gatherings in Seattle. From time to time my agenda changes because of webinars I chose to listen online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to achieve two main goals while planning my time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the day as similar to ordinary work day as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform only professionally valid activities during daytime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such agenda I feel that I do not waste my time and I am no longer afraid of the question “So what do you do all day long (if you are not working)?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I am happy with my unemployment days, I’d rather found a job sooner to fill my 16 hours of personal time with actual work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/here-is-how-i-spend-my-weekdays-as-unemployed.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/here-is-how-i-spend-my-weekdays-as-unemployed.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Late retro of 2014</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Following the tradition, in this post I’m looking back to 2014 to summarize most significant things that happened to me during this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blog&quot;&gt;Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve managed to keep my blog alive! During 2014 I have written 25 blog posts (for 2013 it was 33), though I written less, visits increased almost twice - from 2500 (for 2013) to 4800 unique visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/2014stats-1024x305.png&quot; alt=&quot;stats&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top 3 posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/workshops/games-to-play-during-workshops-and-training.html&quot;&gt;Games to play during workshops and training&lt;/a&gt; (1958 page views)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/workshops/lego-game-for-kanban-workshop.html&quot;&gt;Lego game for Kanban workshop&lt;/a&gt; (409 page views)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/know-how/11.html&quot;&gt;1:1&lt;/a&gt; (316 page views)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;travel&quot;&gt;Travel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was exceptional in terms of traveling for me. Not only I’ve visited 6 countries, was abroad for 54 days, but also I’ve moved to US in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presentations-and-trainings&quot;&gt;Presentations and trainings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I started to give trainings and consulting for companies that want to adopt Agile. I’ve done 3 two-days Agile private trainings for companies and 5 lectures for students. Also made one new presentation on how to deal with challenges (&lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/jelenafiodorova/keep-calm-and-meet-challenge&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-education-and-conferences&quot;&gt;Self-education and conferences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I’ve completed coaching course, took a couple more courses at Coursera. Attended these workshops:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High Performance through Learning by Niels Pflaeging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product management workshop by Bob Marshall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In October became Certified Scrum Professional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/farewell-300x233.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;farewell&quot; class=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was rather a sad moment for me, in October I left Adform and followed my husband to US. He got a job at Amazon, so I decided to look for new career opportunities in Greater Seattle Area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of great moments I had in Adform, meaningful and happy time working with smart people, newest technologies, creating the best ad platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss my great D&amp;amp;D team. In a photo you can see the farewell gift my team made me :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrilled and excited I’m looking forward for 2015 and all the challenges and opportunities it’ll bring.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/late-retro-of-2014.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/late-retro-of-2014.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Everyone needs a mentor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think everyone wants to improve at what he does. Mentoring helps here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;getty embed image left&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#fff;display:inline-block;font-family:&#39;Helvetica Neue&#39;,Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;color:#a7a7a7;font-size:11px;width:100%;max-width:507px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;overflow:hidden;position:relative;height:0;padding:66.666667% 0 0 0;width:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//embed.gettyimages.com/embed/466843081?et=X8SylcMUQu9heFO9H3o4-g&amp;amp;viewMoreLink=on&amp;amp;sig=dayem-Oys5xWmz18W5EtP2oJYyngvMLs5ibL8K8pZzE=&quot; width=&quot;507&quot; height=&quot;338&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;display:inline-block;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin:0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:0;margin:0 0 0 10px;text-align:left;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com/detail/466843081&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;View image&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;gettyimages.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently have heard a presentation about a couple of main principles of Toyota manufacturing processes that is believed helped the company to succeed. Mentoring process is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps every employee to improve his own production process and achieve desirable “target condition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am lucky that everything around me happens in the very best way even when I have no conscious plan for it. Same with mentoring. My mentor found me. Which I am very grateful for. If you are not so very lucky, I suggest to find your mentor yourself. I think it should be more senior (in term of experience) professional than you and you both need to know that mentoring is happening between you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, my mentor was very organized and prepared. We had a mentoring session once per quarter. My mentor had some questions for each session and was taking notes. Every time he started with reminding me what we were talking last time, what I was happy about,  what concerns did I have, then followed by looking into how my situation changed after last time. What I have tried, I have achieved, what doubts do I have, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though first sessions were weird a bit for me, but later I found it very useful for my development. Sometimes you need to say it loudly in order to get it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks Mats! :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/improvements/everyone-needs-a-mentor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/improvements/everyone-needs-a-mentor.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>improvements</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Organize for Comlexity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally I have a time to put in a post all my thoughts after reading a new book - “Organize for complexity” by Niels Pflaeging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/organize_for_complexity-194x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;organize for complexity&quot; class=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a must read for those, who feel that hierarchies, bonuses, command and control management - is not the right approach for modern organizations to follow and needs to be changed for better performance. You will enrich this list of “things to change” with even more principles and approaches after reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book covers many topics but not too deeply, that’s why it leaves you with more questions than answers after reading it. It will definitely make you think, explore and seek for more information to do the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a couple of quotations, that I find interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-organization is not the “right” term. Better would be: Socially dense market-organization.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social pressure, used correctly: far more powerful that hierarchy, no damaging side-effects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your organization is already networked. It is just not allowed to officially operate as one.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Culture neither is a barrier to change, nor does it encourage change. It can provide hints to what an organization must learn.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understood correctly, leadership in complexity means working the system, not the people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let purpose drive behavior. Not numbers, or manipulative and controlling processes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I already mentioned, this book doesn’t give you a deep and detailed explanation of topics, so I would highly recommend to listen to Niels presentation or webinar or attend a workshop. These together with the book will give you a much better ground for the change you want to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/organize-for-comlexity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/organize-for-comlexity.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Off-site with teams #2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I’ve shared with you my &lt;a href=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/know-how/off-site-with-teams.html&quot;&gt;experiment&lt;/a&gt; of gathering all my teams together and having a fresh look at products we build. So this is a second try. Different time, different place, but the goal stays the same: share ideas, educate each other, team-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/margiokrantas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;margiokrantas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are pushing scrum into teams for a quite long time and it starts to work as expected, you usually get a non desirable side effect of it - teams become isolated, communicate less with each other, become too focused on a team goal and try to improve team performance. That’s why you need something that gathers different teams in one room and gives them a possibility to get to know each other again. For the second time I have tried gathering my teams for such extended knowledge sharing session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion it worked just fine, we had various discussions on business and tech topics, reviewed what we achieved, thought about the future. Here a simplified agenda of our off-site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product Owners presenting new products. 10 minutes for each product. What is it? Vision. Why? Benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product Owners presenting current products. 10 minutes stories of the products with overview of recently released major features and further essential plans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scrum Masters (or someone from the team) presenting products from tech perspective. 10 minutes technical overview of your products: how are/will they be developed, architecture overview, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Success stories. All teams (it could be anyone from the team) prepare a short  ~5-7 minutes overview on how you product succeeds in different countries, how the usage is changing, how much money it’s earning, etc. – anything you find interesting and exciting about you products.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remembering the promises from the last event. Watching recorded video followed with a short update of what was actually done from those promises – anyone from the teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And then for 2 hours discuss within teams. Form team’s targets for future (3-6 months) and make new promises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to film every session and presentation and after some editing put it on company’s internal wiki for other teams to learn about what we do. Actually I find it very useful in may ways: for the team to step up out of daily routine and think about the future, for every attendee to learn about related teams, for teams outside the event - to learn about our products. And moreover, we use this filmed material for newcomers to teach them about teams, products, people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have tried such events - I encourage to try it :) it fun and useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/off-site-with-teams-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/off-site-with-teams-2.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Establishing estimates</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a short introduction to one of many techniques how to establish estimates (in my teams we make estimation of size, not the duration of the task) - White elephant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;getty embed image left&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#fff;display:inline-block;font-family:&#39;Helvetica Neue&#39;,Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;color:#a7a7a7;font-size:11px;width:100%;max-width:414px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;overflow:hidden;position:relative;height:0;padding:100.000000% 0 0 0;width:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//embed.gettyimages.com/embed/136643000?et=Ba6f-JkqTuNfkhJEqF_-tw&amp;amp;viewMoreLink=on&amp;amp;sig=dGyiXxBkJOblc56I2Y7Y-UgfeaIs4zGruH85nHJwyjY=&quot; width=&quot;414&quot; height=&quot;414&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;display:inline-block;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin:0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:0;margin:0 0 0 10px;text-align:left;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com/detail/136643000&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;View image&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;gettyimages.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique is taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_elephant_gift_exchange&quot;&gt;White elephant gift exchange&lt;/a&gt; party game. You can use “White elephant” within your team when you need to estimate upcoming work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I had an initial estimation session with one team (they are in the beginning of Agile adoption). This was a team of  7 members and they had 39 items (of current and upcoming work) to estimate.
We started with answering these two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the purpose of estimation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do we want to estimate: size, duration, complexity, velocity, etc. For us it is size we estimate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we decided what measures did we want to use: T-shirt sizing (XS, S, M, L, XL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used simple rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talks one at a time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone in round-robin manner:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Takes a card from pile (or already placed)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reads the task loudly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Put into one column (XS, S, M, L, XL) if hard to decide – put into M&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Explain why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If task was moved 3 times – it cannot be moved again, meaning that we need to discuss more about it afterwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat while everyone agrees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve managed to finish estimating in less than half an hour.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-c.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xfa1/10684256_695100200581050_1671519976_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;task board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this session we achieved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common understanding about all the tasks we have in scope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common feeling how to estimate relatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualization of how much loaded with work are our team members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information for further future when we will be figuring out what is our velocity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The list of unclear/need to discuss tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things  to keep in mind while estimating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compare stories to get estimates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use more than one example&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Group similar sized user stories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/workshops/establishing-estimates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/workshops/establishing-estimates.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>workshops</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>1:1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is how my calendar looks like the week when I’m having meetings with each member of my team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/performance-evaluations.png&quot; alt=&quot;performance evaluations&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually I do 1:1 (one-on-ones) twice a year with each of my team members. So how do I do it? Differently each time. Couple of years ago I’ve been using “Moving motivators” as Jurgen Appelo suggests in his Management 3.0 course (please find instructions &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.management30.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/04-Moving-Motivators-A4-v2.00.pdf%20&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Last time I did &lt;a href=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/know-how/walking-meetings-are-just-great.html&quot;&gt;Walking meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/BeBetterLeader/img/post_img/coffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;coffee&quot; class=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;
This time we just took a coffee and went for a walk along the river. I prepare for each of these meetings: gather feedback (if needed), look through notes from previous talks, gather ideas what I want to pass and think about questions I want to get answers to. This time I asked these 5 questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you happy here?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are you proud of from the last year?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there any blockers on your way?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I or a new Development manager help you?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you would consider leaving our company, for what would you do that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 01:00:59 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/11.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/11.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Keep calm and meet challenges</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been asked to share how do I manage incidents and solve problems with my teams. In this blog post you can find a short summary of how do I usually do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; First, there are 3 approaches I follow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every challenge, incident or problem you face - helps you grow, it’s a level-up for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worrying never helps. Action does.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You may choose one of two: either being a part of a problem, or a part of a solution. I choose - solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So having this in mind all the time - helps to move on to mechanical part of problem solving very fast. In presentation I cover what steps do I usually take and what tools and techniques I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the slides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 1px solid #CCC; border-width: 1px; margin-bottom: 5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; src=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/38401264&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/presentations/keep-calm-and-meet-challengies.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/presentations/keep-calm-and-meet-challengies.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>presentations</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
