<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Be a Better Leader</title>
    <description>Practical notes on leadership improvements</description>
    <link>http://www.bebetterleader.com/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.bebetterleader.com/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 18:37:04 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 18:37:04 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>73 Practical Tips to Become a Better Leader</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I gave a talk at ‘Agile day 2013’ conference in  Vilnius on how to improve constantly and what things to try out if you want to create an environment and processes for effective product development. Check out the slides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[slideshare id=20923934&amp;amp;doc=73tipstobecomebetterleader-130510075458-phpapp01]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 01:12:37 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bebetterleader.com/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll/presentations/2013/05/14/73-tips-to-become-a-better-leader/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bebetterleader.com/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll/presentations/2013/05/14/73-tips-to-become-a-better-leader/</guid>
        
        
        <category>presentations</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World!</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;philosophy-of-improvement&quot;&gt;Philosophy of improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very important to constantly improve in order to be productive and achieve best results. One can improve environment, tools and processes. Sometimes even a small change in management can result in huge productivity boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear reader, please let me introduce to you my notes of becoming a better manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 10 years I’ve been performing various roles in software development: a developer at the beginning, then an analyst and project manager, and later an assistant manager for development department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I work as a Program Development Manager in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adform.com&quot;&gt;Adform&lt;/a&gt;. I run a department of 3 teams (17 highly skilled developers). We develop a product for online advertising - it’s a software as a service to manage and monitor online ad campaigns. My teams focus on DSP (Demand Side Platform) and DI (Direct Integrations). These are highly technically challenging parts of a system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working in this position for 3 years now. During these years I’ve tried lots of things and keep on trying. Recently I decided to track my experiments and findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-i-write&quot;&gt;Why do I write?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are basically two main targets I wish to achieve by starting a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first - to build a set of practices for myself and others. Usually when time passes I do not remember the details, the reasoning, and how it went - just consequences remain. So I think blogging is a good tool to track that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second - to share my know-how. Maybe you would be interested in my findings and try those practices for yourself or give a feedback and share your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-might-be-interested&quot;&gt;Who might be interested?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these notes might be of an interest to development managers, team leads and developers acting in Scrum master role, in other words to everyone who is organizing and improving the process of software development, building and supervising development teams. Newby managers may use this blog as an introduction book.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bebetterleader.com/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll/other/2013/03/12/hello-world/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bebetterleader.com/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll/other/2013/03/12/hello-world/</guid>
        
        
        <category>other</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
