<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Be a Better Leader</title>
    <description>Practical notes on leadership improvements</description>
    <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 16:53:46 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 16:53:46 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Here is how I spend my weekdays as unemployed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was always curious what do people do all day long if they do not work!? For me it was frightening question. Since I can remember all my weekdays were preoccupied with important activities and rather strict schedule: first, school and after school lectures, then university and different kinds of part time jobs and later, professionally developing software for ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://files.bebetterleader.com/media/vintage-housewife-276x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image courtesy of Austin Fashion Week&quot; /&gt; &lt;small&gt;Image courtesy of Austin Fashion Week&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all the weekdays were predefined for me: wakeup in the morning, travel to work, work, travel home, yoga class, two-three hours of a free personal time, go to sleep. Roughly rounding: 11 hours work related activities and 5 hours of non work related activities and 8 hours for sleep. So what do you do 16 hours a day if you don’t work!!??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 months ago I decided to leave my dream job and move to Seattle in search for even better one. So for 5 months I’m unemployed and have 16 hours of a personal time everyday in my possession. And believe me, from the day one of my unemployment I started getting this frightening “What do you do all day long” question very often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2015/01/06/upshot/how-nonemployed-americans-spend-their-weekdays-men-vs-women.html?_r=0&amp;amp;abt=0002&amp;amp;abg=0&quot;&gt;interesting statistics on how do Americans spend their weekdays&lt;/a&gt; and decided to share my daily routine. Here is how my weekday agenda looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7:00 Wake up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7:30 - 8:30 Brisk walk (I escort my husband to his office and come back home)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8:30 - 12:00 &lt;strong&gt;News &amp;amp; job search&lt;/strong&gt;: catching-up with news and blogs on software development and management (mostly, via Feedly) or perform job search activities, such as: searching for new connections on LinkedIn, writing emails to recruiters, filling in job applications forms, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00 - 13:00 Workout in a gym &amp;amp; short daily yoga class (while working out in a gym I try to listen to various podcasts)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:00 - 13:30 Lunch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:30 - 15:00 &lt;strong&gt;Listening to lectures&lt;/strong&gt; (currently it’s Princeton University Algorithms course provided by Coursera or MIT Open Courseware Computer Science lectures)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15:00 - 18:30 &lt;strong&gt;Programming&lt;/strong&gt; (I decided to learn Ruby, so now I’m implementing various classic algorithms, data structures and solve interesting coding challenges using Ruby)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/github-300x181.png&quot; alt=&quot;github&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not say, that all days are the same, the energy level is high and I wish to do all these activities instead of procrastinating on the internet or doing something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/lounge-150x150.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lounge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when these days come, I go out to work in some public place: either lounge areas in my building or some coffee shop in a neighborhood. This helps to overcome laziness and to stay focused on a task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/starbucks-150x150.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;starbucks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this agenda, at least twice a month I attend different Agile, Project Management, Software Development Management and similar meet-ups and gatherings in Seattle. From time to time my agenda changes because of webinars I chose to listen online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to achieve two main goals while planning my time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the day as similar to ordinary work day as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform only professionally valid activities during daytime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such agenda I feel that I do not waste my time and I am no longer afraid of the question “So what do you do all day long (if you are not working)?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I am happy with my unemployment days, I’d rather found a job sooner to fill my 16 hours of personal time with actual work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/here-is-how-i-spend-my-weekdays-as-unemployed.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/here-is-how-i-spend-my-weekdays-as-unemployed.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Everyone needs a mentor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think everyone wants to improve at what he does. Mentoring helps here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;getty embed image&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#fff;display:inline-block;font-family:&#39;Helvetica Neue&#39;,Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;color:#a7a7a7;font-size:11px;width:100%;max-width:507px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;overflow:hidden;position:relative;height:0;padding:66.666667% 0 0 0;width:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//embed.gettyimages.com/embed/466843081?et=X8SylcMUQu9heFO9H3o4-g&amp;amp;viewMoreLink=on&amp;amp;sig=dayem-Oys5xWmz18W5EtP2oJYyngvMLs5ibL8K8pZzE=&quot; width=&quot;507&quot; height=&quot;338&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;display:inline-block;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin:0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:0;margin:0 0 0 10px;text-align:left;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com/detail/466843081&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;View image&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;gettyimages.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently have heard a presentation about a couple of main principles of Toyota manufacturing processes that is believed helped the company to succeed. Mentoring process is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps every employee to improve his own production process and achieve desirable “target condition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am lucky that everything around me happens in the very best way even when I have no conscious plan for it. Same with mentoring. My mentor found me. Which I am very grateful for. If you are not so very lucky, I suggest to find your mentor yourself. I think it should be more senior (in term of experience) professional than you and you both need to know that mentoring is happening between you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, my mentor was very organized and prepared. We had a mentoring session once per quarter. My mentor had some questions for each session and was taking notes. Every time he started with reminding me what we were talking last time, what I was happy about,  what concerns did I have, then followed by looking into how my situation changed after last time. What I have tried, I have achieved, what doubts do I have, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though first sessions were weird a bit for me, but later I found it very useful for my development. Sometimes you need to say it loudly in order to get it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks Mats! :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/improvements/everyone-needs-a-mentor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/improvements/everyone-needs-a-mentor.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>improvements</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Establishing estimates</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a short introduction to one of many techniques how to establish estimates (in my teams we make estimation of size, not the duration of the task) - White elephant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;getty embed image&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#fff;display:inline-block;font-family:&#39;Helvetica Neue&#39;,Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;color:#a7a7a7;font-size:11px;width:100%;max-width:414px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;overflow:hidden;position:relative;height:0;padding:100.000000% 0 0 0;width:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//embed.gettyimages.com/embed/136643000?et=Ba6f-JkqTuNfkhJEqF_-tw&amp;amp;viewMoreLink=on&amp;amp;sig=dGyiXxBkJOblc56I2Y7Y-UgfeaIs4zGruH85nHJwyjY=&quot; width=&quot;414&quot; height=&quot;414&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;display:inline-block;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin:0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:0;margin:0 0 0 10px;text-align:left;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com/detail/136643000&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;View image&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gettyimages.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&quot;&gt;gettyimages.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique is taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_elephant_gift_exchange&quot;&gt;White elephant gift exchange&lt;/a&gt; party game. You can use “White elephant” within your team when you need to estimate upcoming work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I had an initial estimation session with one team (they are in the beginning of Agile adoption). This was a team of  7 members and they had 39 items (of current and upcoming work) to estimate.
We started with answering these two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the purpose of estimation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do we want to estimate: size, duration, complexity, velocity, etc. For us it is size we estimate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we decided what measures did we want to use: T-shirt sizing (XS, S, M, L, XL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used simple rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talks one at a time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone in round-robin manner:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Takes a card from pile (or already placed)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reads the task loudly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Put into one column (XS, S, M, L, XL) if hard to decide – put into M&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Explain why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If task was moved 3 times – it cannot be moved again, meaning that we need to discuss more about it afterwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat while everyone agrees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-c.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xfa1/10684256_695100200581050_1671519976_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Task board&quot; /&gt;We’ve managed to finish estimating in less than half an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this session we achieved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common understanding about all the tasks we have in scope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common feeling how to estimate relatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualization of how much loaded with work are our team members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information for further future when we will be figuring out what is our velocity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The list of unclear/need to discuss tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things  to keep in mind while estimating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compare stories to get estimates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use more than one example&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Group similar sized user stories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/workshops/establishing-estimates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/workshops/establishing-estimates.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>workshops</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>1:1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is how my calendar looks like the week when I’m having meetings with each member of my team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/performance-evaluations.png&quot; alt=&quot;performance evaluations&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually I do 1:1 (one-on-ones) twice a year with each of my team members. So how do I do it? Differently each time. Couple of years ago I’ve been using “Moving motivators” as Jurgen Appelo suggests in his Management 3.0 course (please find instructions &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.management30.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/04-Moving-Motivators-A4-v2.00.pdf%20&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Last time I did &lt;a href=&quot;/know-how/walking-meetings-are-just-great.html&quot;&gt;Walking meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/coffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coffee&quot; /&gt;This time we just took a coffee and went for a walk along the river. I prepare for each of these meetings: gather feedback (if needed), look through notes from previous talks, gather ideas what I want to pass and think about questions I want to get answers to. This time I asked these 5 questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you happy here?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are you proud of from the last year?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there any blockers on your way?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I or a new Development manager help you?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you would consider leaving our company, for what would you do that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 01:00:59 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/11.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/11.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dear dev managers, how fast do your teams grow?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve made some calculations to visualize the dynamics in my teams over the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/employees.png&quot; alt=&quot;Growth graph&quot; title=&quot;Changing number of employees over the year&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been surprised: from 11 to 31 members, from 2 to 5 teams. My question is how fast can we grow in order to satisfy client’s hunger for features, but still keep the comfort for teams and do not increase technical debt of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With every new member we slow down, as well as we increase communication channels. It usually lead us to different misunderstandings and other things such as: everyone having their own style, opinion, vision, speed, quality level, etc. And that’s the price you pay for growing. Some more technical of these differences we can easily unify by introducing coding standards, testing procedures, development processes. But what about soft ones? I have my way of introducing new members to my team, you can find it in this &lt;a href=&quot;/know-how/youre-hired.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s your speed of growing software development teams/departments?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/dear-dev-managers-how-fast-do-your-teams-grow.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/dear-dev-managers-how-fast-do-your-teams-grow.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failed. Never praise for standards</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s very hard to share failures. Half a year has passed and I still feel some embracement and discomfort. But I want to make a note, especially for myself after some years to remember and not to repeat this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/chocolates.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chocolates&quot; /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One evening I was just browsing our GIT repository. Looking through commits, wikis, etc. Pulled one solution, tried to build it - failed. Pulled the second one (other team’s) - tried to build - failed again. And only the third one succeeded: I got all referred libraries downloaded, all need configurations done while building - no errors, very little warnings, everything built and ready to run. Taking into account a couple of failures that happened before - I was absolutely happy with the team, that they were keeping their solutions in good health. So I decided to praise this team. I got a big box of chocolates and went to stand-up meeting all happy next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which was wrong. Never repeat it. No one in a team shared my happiness, they even were frustrated. ‘Why do you complement this standard behavior? We get our salaries for that.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With praising is pretty clear lesson: do not praise for standard behavior, praise for extra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the open question remains: how to encourage teams to keep their solutions in good state if not praising for it? Punish? Promote standards harder? Educate? Push to clean-up?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/experiments/failed-never-praise-for-standards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/experiments/failed-never-praise-for-standards.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiments</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You&#39;re hired</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So you’ve done a huge job - you’ve hired a person. What’s next? And here comes a very important stage - onboarding. This is the time you teach and pass to the person culture, traditions, processes, everything. How do I do it? In 6 simple steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Intro&lt;/strong&gt;. First I like to give an introduction to a new person same day he starts - usual stuff: org structure, who is who, how we are used to work, set some ground rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Learn the product&lt;/strong&gt;. The main assignment for the first two weeks - to learn a product. We arrange extensive trainings for each product of ours for person to know very well what he will be building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Learn the client&lt;/strong&gt;. Trainings are followed by two weeks internship in client support, working as a client support specialist, getting to know the clients and how our product solves their problems and serves their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Learn the team&lt;/strong&gt;. From the very first day person starts working in a team, participating in stand-ups and other meetings team has. I think it is very important for a new team member to start taking tasks from team’s task board (if there are any that fit him) or join a colleague for the pair programming as early as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Fast feedback&lt;/strong&gt;. You don’t want to get a feedback too late. That’s why I schedule recurrent meeting to sync with a new person every 2/3 weeks. This is the time I provide a feedback to a new team member (which I gather from the team in advance) and ask some questions to get to know are we on the right track here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you evaluate your start at the company?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you like the product? Team? Code base? Process? Atmosphere?  Culture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you feel?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Have you expectations been met? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Would you like to change something? What? How? Why haven’t you changed it already? What stops you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Probationary end.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the final stage of the “intensive care” period and here I let the team to decide whether to keep a person in the team or not. You can find more on how do i do it in my previous post &lt;a href=&quot;/know-how/let-team-decide-hire-or-fire.html&quot;&gt;Let team decide: hire or fire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would you like your first months in a company to be?  Or how do you do onboarding?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/youre-hired.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/youre-hired.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A mind of its own</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is another interesting and worth spending time on book I’ve recently read - “A mind of its own” by Cordelia Fine. &lt;a href=&quot;/img/post_img/mind_of_its_own.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/post_img/mind_of_its_own.png&quot; alt=&quot;mind_of_its_own&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take-away out of it: our brain is “multi-dimensional” and knowing these “dimensions” could help you better understand why did you do or say something, or why did you wanted to say or do it, or why did you feel that particular way in various specific situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are these “dimensions”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vain brain&lt;/em&gt; - we all have small positive illusions that make us feel special, disturbing the thought that in truths we are not of more significance in the universe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emotional brain&lt;/em&gt; - usually we have no particular information why we are feeling emotionally strived, feelings triggered by one event can be wrongly used while judging other matters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Immoral brain&lt;/em&gt; - it just not serve our psychological need to feel that the life is fair and secure, it also assists in maintaining all-important sense of moral superiority.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deluded brain&lt;/em&gt; - even people with healthy brain think irrationally and unscientifically in particular situations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pigheaded brain&lt;/em&gt; - we are tend to stick to our important beliefs even if they are not true anymore, we think we know it all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secretive brain&lt;/em&gt; - actually our unconscious is faster than we, smarter than we and more powerful than we, it may even control us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weak-willed brain&lt;/em&gt; - there are many reasons for will to fail us, that’s why we need to develop good habits to enhance a willpower.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bigoted brain&lt;/em&gt; - though one might come to treat others fairly and justly despite of any stereotypes in some situations, we still need to work hard on controlling unconscious effects of stereotyping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is full of examples and results of different researches to support each of these 8 “brains”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say it’s a good read for everyone who spends at least a little time in self-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/a-mind-of-its-own.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/books/a-mind-of-its-own.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Walking meetings are just great!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I wrote a short &lt;a href=&quot;/know-how/walking-and-talking.html&quot;&gt;Walking meetings&lt;/a&gt; post about my intention to conduct mid-year evaluation meetings with colleagues outside the office while walking. So here are some insights how it went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In details: I scheduled these meetings in advance (as always) with some guided questions to gather up the ideas for talk, noticing everyone that we would be outside. Each meeting went by the same schema: we grab a coffee and went to a quiet place - by the river mostly. Everything else as in usual 1:1 - small talk, questions, answers, overview of what happened, plans for future, mutual feedback, etc. In comparison to traditional evaluation meetings, these were more relaxed, easy going, we discussed more things than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely not for every possible meeting. When you take notes, or show some data, or there are more than 3 attendees - you need something else. But if you are just talking, asking/answering questions - go out! Just remember to check the weather and find not very busy place for a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: in total I went 25 km this time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/walking-meetings-are-just-great.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/know-how/walking-meetings-are-just-great.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>know-how</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Games to play during workshops and training</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of exercises and games you can try playing with a small group of people during workshops, training or team buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;games&quot;&gt;Games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These games take from 1 to 4 hours. All are good to learn different Agile methods in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make teams. In a team: one designer, one messenger, others are artists. Designer sees the requirements - picture and explains to artists via messenger in written form, no verbal communication. Artists draw the picture according to description they got from messenger. Do a couple of messages. Do review. Do retro. Repeat with improvements.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: learn Agile, teamwork, communication, break the “rules”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make teams. In a team: product owner, scrum master, others workers. Objective: create a travel agency brochure or a plain, or any other product. Work according Scrum, make at least 3 sprints, or play until the product is fully created.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: learn Scrum, teamwork, improvements&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make Lego houses using kanban in teams. Here are detailed &lt;a href=&quot;/workshops/lego-game-for-kanban-workshop.html&quot;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt; how to run it.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: learn kanban, teamwork&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dynamic-physical-exercises&quot;&gt;Dynamic physical exercises&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very short up to 10 minutes. Very good between sessions, to stretch out bit and to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Select 2 persons from a group and try to position yourself between them.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: dynamic, move&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Select a person from the group and try to get behind him.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: dynamic, move, feel the constant change&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;team-building&quot;&gt;Team building&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium long exercises up to 1 hour, very good in teams for team building, knowing each other better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every one stands in a circle. No one is allowed to talk more than saying a number. The objective: count from 1 up to 15 (this number may differ according to participants). Each can say one number at a time. If sequence is broken - start all over again from 1.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: nonverbal communication, teamwork&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On pieces of paper write each participants name (each name on different piece). Pass paper around. Everyone writes down what does he appreciate about person named on this piece of paper.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: feedback, team building, positive emotions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Describe the picture. Show a picture to one of the group. Invite another participant, the first guy has to tell what has he seen on a picture. Then first guys goes away, third comes. Second guy tells what he has heard. This way information is being passed through everyone in a group. Show picture to everyone at the end. It’s cool to take a video, and then analyze it together and see what phrases make what changes.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: verbal communication, team building&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everyone writes down two things about himself: true and lie. One reads all things loud - everyone guesses who is this about.
&lt;em&gt;Good for&lt;/em&gt;: team building, knowing each other better&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know any other games to play in a team?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/workshops/games-to-play-during-workshops-and-training.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jelenabarinova.github.io/BeBetterLeader/workshops/games-to-play-during-workshops-and-training.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>workshops</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
